Guide to the Donna Stein Papers on Thomas Wilfred
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Donna Stein papers on Thomas Wilfred
1914-2001
MS 2036
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4.33
(8 boxes)
The papers document Stein's professional and scholarly work on kinetic light artist Thomas Wilfred. The majority of the collection consists of research materials on Wilfred and his art work, including scholarly and popular magazine articles, writings by Wilfred, and photographs of Wilfred's compositions and studio. Included are materials from two exhibitions of Wilfred's work that Stein curated for the Corcoran Gallery of Art in Washington, D.C. and the Museum of Modern Art in New York, New York. Finally the collection contains Stein's master's thesis on Wilfred, and professional correspondence regarding Wilfred's artwork, the exhibitions, and professional publications. Materials cover from 1914 to 2001, with the bulk from 1962 to 1972.
Stein, Donna
Scope and Contents
The papers document Stein's professional and scholarly work on kinetic light artist Thomas Wilfred. The majority of the collection consists of research materials on Wilfred and his art work, including scholarly and popular magazine articles, writings by Wilfred, and photographs of Wilfred's compositions and studio. Included are materials from two exhibitions of Wilfred's work that Stein curated for the Corcoran Gallery of Art in Washington, D.C. and the Museum of Modern Art in New York, New York. Finally the collection contains Stein's master's thesis on Wilfred, and professional correspondence regarding Wilfred's artwork, the exhibitions, and professional publications. Materials cover from 1914 to 2001, with the bulk from 1962 to 1972.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in four series and one addition: I. Stein's thesis materials on Thomas Wilfred, 1950-1971. II. Correspondence, 1950-2001. III. Exhibition files, 1965-1996. IV. Research materials, 1914-1981.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Donna Stein, 2015, 2017.
Related Materials
Related materials: Thomas Wilfred Papers (MS 1375).
Biographical / Historical
Thomas Wilfred
Thomas Wilfred was a kinetic light artist whose body of work consists of compositions that he called "Lumia." He was born Richard Edgar Løvstrøm on June 18, 1889 in Naestved, Denmark. Wilfred trained as both an artist and a musician, starting both drawing classes and piano lessons in 1903. In 1908 he moved to Paris, France, to study painting, sculpture, and voice at the Sorbonne, although he never earned a degree there. Beyond the piano, he also learned how to play the archlute, a European folk instrument. Both his art training and musical training would play important roles in developing his Lumia compositions. He also was a freelance newspaper journalist and wrote and published poetry. In 1913, he took the professional name Thomas Wilfred for his musical career, which he would continue to use as an artist. He served in the Royal Danish Army during World War I. After finishing his military service in 1916, he moved to the United States.
Wilfred's earliest memory was of his father using a faceted crystal egg as a prism to project colors on a wall to entertain Wilfred. He started experimenting with refracting light in 1905 with a cigar box, an incandescent lamp, colored glass, and lenses. He also studied theoretical works on light that related colors on the light spectrum with musical scales. His work progressed to projecting different colors on a screen by playing a keyboard instrument he built called a clavilux. Wilfred started performing at his first studio in South Huntington, New York as well as performing at concerts at the Neighborhood Playhouse in New York, New York, Queen's Hall in London, England, and the Royal Opera House in Copenhagen, Denmark. He also created several standalone compositions, many as commissions. In 1930, he founded the Art Institute of Light to serve as a place of study for artists wishing to work in Lumia. Wilfred died on August 15, 1968 in Nyack, New York.
Donna Stein
Donna Stein is the Deputy Director of the Wende Museum in Culver City, California. She is also an art historian, art critic, and curator. She has studied at the University of California, Los Angeles and the Institute of Fine Arts at New York University. She has curated exhibitions in museums in the United States, Europe, and Asia.
Art -- Exhibitions; Kinetic art; Light art; Stein, Donna; Wilfred, Thomas, 1889-1968; Corcoran Gallery of Art; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.)
- Stein's thesis materials on Thomas Wilfred, 1950-1971; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the outline and rough draft of Stein's master's thesis written while studying at the Institute of Fine Arts at New York University, and related correspondence with artist Thomas Wilfred. The thesis materials include a typed outline and typed drafts of each thesis chapter as well as handwritten drafts on legal pad sheets. Correspondence with Wilfred includes interview questions, diagrams of compositions, and edits of specific parts of Stein's thesis. Materials are arranged alphabetically.
  - Outline and rough draft of master's thesis, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Research correspondence with Thomas Wilfred, 1950-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1950-2001; Series II
  This series includes correspondence with individuals related to the loan and maintenance of Wilfred's compositions for Stein's exhibitions, requests of Stein for assistance with research on Wilfred, and requests of Stein for assistance with further exhibitions of Wilfred's work. There is also a small amount of correspondence regarding Stein's manuscript review of an article on Wilfred by Stephen Eskilson for Leonardo journal. The series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Ars Studio, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Conway, John, 1950-1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Epstein, Eugene, 1964-1969, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Land, Richard, 1965-1971 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Mazzia, Valentino Don Bosco, 1959-1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Moritz, William, 1977-1986 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Review of Leonardo article, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Wilfred's artwork, 1968-1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Exhibition files, 1965-1996; Series III
  This series comprises materials related to two exhibitions of Wilfred's artwork that Stein curated at the Corcoran Gallery of Art in Washington, D.C. and the Museum of Modern Art in New York, New York. Materials include photographs and drawings of compositions and composition schematics, catalog texts and proofs, reviews of the exhibitions, and press releases. Materials are arranged by site of exhibition and alphabetically therein.
  - Corcoran exhibition
    - Bills and invoices, 1969-1971 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Catalog text and proofs, Circa 1969-circa 1971 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
    - Correspondence and related notes on compositions, 1965-1996 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
    - Critical reviews, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Negotiations, 1969-1971 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Press release, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Prints and transparencies of technical drawings for exhibit installation, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Prints of technical drawings and related photographs and correspondence, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Museum of Modern Art exhibition
    - Installation photographs, Circa 1971 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Press release and checklist, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Research materials, 1914-1981; Series IV
  This series comprises research materials for different projects related to Wilfred. A significant portion of this series includes bibliographic note cards composed by Stein. Other materials include photographs of Wilfred's artwork and studio, articles on Wilfred, writings by Wilfred, including his manuscript, Lumia, the Art of Light, and chronologies and lists of Wilfred's artwork compiled by Stein and/or Wilfred. There is also information on other kinetic light artists, including Frank Malina and Nicolas Schöffer. Materials are arranged alphabetically.
  - Articles on light
    - General, 1914-1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Articles mentioning Wilfred, 1918-1968 (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
  - Articles related to Wilfred, 1930-1965 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Bibliography, Circa 1965-1970 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Biography of Wilfred, 1922-1971 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Excerpts from Wilfred's writings, Circa 1919-circa 1968 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Exhibitions list, Circa 1971 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Joe's Lights, 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Museum of Modern Art painting and sculpture acquisition catalog, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Museum of Modern Art newsletter article and related memoranda, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Note cards, Circa 1960-circa 1971 (Box 6–7)
  - Other kinetic light artists
    - General, 1964-1977 (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
    - Malina, Frank, 1963-1981 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Schöffer, Nicolas, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Photographs and negatives of Wilfred's West Nyack studio, Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Photographs and transparencies of Wilfred's Lumia compositions, Undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Publicity on Thomas Wilfred, Circa 1920-1968 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Reiback, Earl, 1970-1974 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Revised manuscript of Lumia, the Art of Light by Thomas Wilfred, Circa 1945-circa 1947 (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
  - Wise Gallery pamphlets, 1964-1970 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Additional material, 1967-1971; Accession 2017-M-045
  - Exhibition catalog and gallery information, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Slides of Wilfred's artwork, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)